My sweet ...
This is the blessed spot where we met 17 years ago .
Only the leopard is new .
Kind nature long ago relieved the other of his shackles .
You see , dear , I keep talking of nature 's benevolence ,
of merciful fate , of the kindness of God .
We judge and criticise others , rebuke them .
But what about we ourselves ?
I always have the feeling that I do so little for you .
- We are not doing badly , Roman . - Not badly ...
Thanks to your dowry ,
to your blessed mother 's support
and the support of your aunt .
Perhaps I furnished our apartment ,
but that 's about all .
Dear , I must take care of you . Zina is 16 , Mili 14 .
Come now , children ...
Cages are for mute creatures .
I 've discovered how I can increase my income .
I 'll hire an agent on commission .
It will be Mr. Strauss .
A good , decent man .
I 'll invite him to our party .
We are a lovely and blessed family ,
but I always have the feeling that I do so little for you .
FILMOVE STUDIO BARRANDOV presents
as
THE CREMATOR
Based on the novel by
Screenplay by
Starring
Costume designer Wardrobe
Production Designer Make-up
Art Director Assistant Art Director
Edited by
Sound
Music by
Played by Conducted by
Production Manager
Director of Photography
Directed by
Not a drop of liquor , Mr. Rybka , just tea .
Mr. Prachar is a poor man .
You may serve weak coffee ... to those willing to pay .
What about my cream coffin ?
Smokers must also do without .
You 'll neither drink nor smoke during eternity .
How about next to this charming lady .
I still didn 't get my cream coffin .
Indeed , Mr. Strauss , working in contact with confectioners
must be rather pleasant .
But why not offer such sweet people something
else ?
Not goods but something more personal for those fine people .
Offer your treats
and then hand them a flyer with an application form .
COME JOIN US !
You 'll get five crowns
for every subscriber .
Excuse me , Mr. Strauss . Excuse me , my angel .
A friend from the war , Mr. Reinke , has arrived .
We fought together for Austria .
A warm welcome ! I haven 't seen you for ages .
- You must come and visit . - Oh , paunchy ...
Afterward , we must introduce our wives .
Mr. Rybka ...
What 's this ? I thought we were going to a concert .
Well ... they 're playing , aren 't they ?
Are you kidding ?
A philharmonic is an orchestra . I see ... how many musicians ?
Four !
The others might turn up ... ... maybe .
I am sure you love music , Mr. Strauss .
Sensitive people do .
The poor , pitiful souls
who die without knowing Schubert , or Liszt ...
Are you by any chance related ? To Johann Strauss ? Or Richard ?
Composer of ' Der Rosenkavalier ' ?
No , I 'm sorry to say , Mr. Kopfrkingl .
- But I love their music . - Yes ?
Anyway , the applications ...
People 's suffering , Mr. Strauss , is another matter ,
and animals suffer , too .
I have a wonderful book on Tibet .
This is Potala ,
the Dalai-Lama 's palace .
Lhasa .
You can read it like the Bible .
God knew what he was talking about when he said :
" Remember , thou art dust and to dust thou shalt return . "
Dear friends , a crematorium is pleasing to our Lord ,
helping Him to hasten our transformation into dust .
Some object , saying that Christ was buried , not cremated .
Quite a different matter , dear friends .
I tell those good people : They embalmed our Saviour ,
wrapped Him in a shroud and interred Him in a cave .
But none of you will be interred in a cave
or wrapped in a shroud .
My dear friends ,
we live in a humane country that builds crematoria .
But not without reason , and not to visit like a museum .
After life 's tribulations , they allow people to lie down quietly
and be transformed into dust .
I have a wonderful book on Tibet - page 38 , for example :
" Suffering is an evil we must be rid of , or at least alleviate .
" The sooner a man turns to dust the sooner he is free ,
" transformed ,
" enlightened
" reincarnated ... "
Animals , too . It takes 20 years in a grave
but just 75 minutes in a crematorium .
Well , dear friends ...
to humanity 's happiness .
Now , dear friends , enjoy the lovely music and dancing .
Partake of the refreshments , and may no one feel lonely .
Good bye .
- A pleasant and witty man . - And how he has suffered .
He had to go on disability because of an ulcerated liver
... or was it kidneys ?
Well , something connected with urine .
Then he lost his wife and son to fever . You don 't like it ?
I could increase his commission if he does well .
Jews are good businessmen .
You think he 's a Jew , dearest ? Strauss isn 't a Jewish name .
A name means nothing .
You call me Lakme instead of Marie .
You want me to call you Roman instead of Karel .
Because I 'm romantic and love beauty , my dear .
That 's the one .
And that noble face .
We 're framing it for the Japanese Embassy .
Yes , that 's the one .
It 's Emiliano Chamorro , president of Nicaragua .
Yes , it 's financial officer Louis Marin ,
Minister of Pensions under Poincare .
But it says on the frame he 's the Nicaraguan president ...
- Never mind that , Mr ... - Holy . - What ? - Holy .
Never mind , Mr. Holy , just cover the name with some tape .
Ah , yes , and something else .
This is the Cremation Law . Please frame it for me ,
and decorate it with some nice sombre pattern .
Yes , yes ...
I imagined something more cheerful .
I bought you some pictures , my angel .
With my first extra income ,
so our home would be even more beautiful .
So Zina 's practicing .
What a talented child .
Mili isn 't home ?
He 's out with Jan , Dr. Bettelheim 's nephew .
At least he isn 't wandering around .
Jan is a decent boy who won 't go farther than the bridge .
- Who 's this ? - The President of Nicaragua .
Let 's put him ...
I think he 'll go here , dearest .
- And where will we hang this ? - In the bathroom .
Do you know , my angels ...
this bathroom is the nicest room we have ?
I don 't know , a bouquet might be better .
Or a hunting scene
pursuing a deer .
And how 's Enchantress ?
Don 't let the poor animal suffer .
Would you like some too ?
Give it to Enchantress then . It 's yesterday 's , anyway .
Help yourselves . May I ?
Prague statisticians say married men live longer .
We 're lucky , Walter , and we should thank our lovely ladies .
Without them we 'd die sooner .
When I remember , Walter , how we enlisted in the Great War ...
how we fought and died ...
how our poor horses suffered ...
It all seems unbelievable .
Peace , justice and happiness should reign in the world .
They don 't drop like manna from heaven . We must fight for them .
Take Austria . Joining the Reich was only the first step .
The Fuehrer is a political genius .
He has rid his huge nation of poverty and unemployment .
Haven 't you seen our Party flyers ?
That 's Louis Marin , former Minister of Pensions .
I bought it at Mr. Holy 's frame shop . He 's a widower .
Our nation was wronged after the war , and those
with German blood in their veins must put the wrong right .
COME JOIN US
Have some almonds .
You 'd rather hear about some sensational death , eh ?
Life is full of tragedies , Mrs. Reinke .
Mr. Strauss went on disability , then lost his wife and child .
I don 't know ... Our children go to Czech schools .
We only speak Czech at home , like right now .
All my books are in Czech ...
even my book on Tibet .
Our blood is Czech too .
Investigate and you 'll find at least one drop of German blood .
Perhaps ...
perhaps a drop .
Well , a truly sensitive person feels even that drop .
I 've got to see Goermann . He 's meeting the Minister in Berlin .
This republic is an obstacle to our deliverance .
But that would take too long to explain .
I wanted to tell you something interesting .
Siamese twins were born ; two heads , two sets of limbs ...
Poor kids , a life twice blessed .
- Where 've you been , Mili ? - Right here .
Jan and I were looking at cars ...
Pity you missed a noteworthy conversation .
Mr. Reinke also went to high school before going to college .
He is meeting a Mr. Goermann ... and you 're behind in German .
We speak Czech at home , but you should learn German .
It 's a huge nation .
Ah , Mr. Strauss !
Go on , go on .
See how successful the poor man is .
- Good day . - Welcome , Mr. Dvorak .
Don 't be frightened . I 'll initiate you very gently .
- This is our porter , Mr. Vrana . - Good day .
He has liver trouble , poor man .
I 've been coming to this temple of death for 15 years ,
and every time I enter a holy feeling enshrouds me .
It 's like my marriage .
We 've been together for 17 years ,
and it 's still just as beautiful
as the day we met at the leopard 's cage .
Come , Mr. Dvorak , nothing to be afraid of .
You have chosen a beautiful , noble profession .
But one full of responsibilities .
Good day .
That 's Mr. Fenek , a morphine addict .
Have you heard ? The Allies are pushing for appeasement .
Don 't worry . It will all turn out fine .
Even I might have a drop of German blood .
One can 't help one 's origins .
No coat , Mr. Dvorak ? We 'll find one and I 'll show you around .
Mrs. Liskova ... How about coming too ?
You don 't know how our equipment works either .
It 's not necessary for cleaning , Mr. Kopfrkingl .
Let 's go then , Mr. Dvorak .
May I smoke ?
Of course , if it makes you happy ...
No thanks , I don 't smoke or drink . I 'm a total abstainer .
We can hear the ceremony through that speaker .
Beautiful music everywhere ... Do you like music ?
Mr. Dvorak ? Sensitive people love music .
I really love it .
That 's nothing , just Mrs. Lesetinska practicing .
This lets down the catafalque .
Upstairs is the world of the survivors .
Our work begins down here .
The furnaces always remind me of the ovens used
for the baking of our daily bread .
That 's our timetable .
A schedule of death no one can avoid ...
unless he 's buried in the ground .
Come , Mr. Dvorak .
We have two gas furnaces which can transform
the deceased into dust in an hour and 15 minutes .
We take a break in the afternoon ,
and you can breathe fresh air in the cemetery .
These little windows allow us to see inside .
There 's nothing to see now , Mr. Dvorak . You must wait
for a nice cremation .
The ashes are packed into these canisters .
But the soul is not . It 's floating in the ether ,
free of the bonds of suffering . Free and purified it seeks
another body .
Here are this afternoon 's coffins .
The first is upstairs waiting for the surviving family
to say their goodbyes .
But some coffins are not sent for viewing .
As you see , these are already nailed shut .
Just leave it there , Mr. Dvorak .
It may come in handy .
Today we cremate Miss Strunna . Can you give me a hand ?
Here she is . I already saw her yesterday .
Her complexion is remarkably rosy ,
as if she were alive .
As if she might awaken ...
and rise .
You may think she 's not really dead ,
but you would be in error , Mr. Dvorak .
She has been pronounced dead ,
and it is our duty to cremate her .
It would be very unlucky if Miss Strunna were still alive ,
as she had her whole life ahead of her .
It would only be lucky if she were to have suffered .
Suffering is a great evil and we must try to alleviate it .
Don 't worry , Mr. Dvorak , Miss Strunna is , I suppose
really dead .
Such mistakes usually don 't happen nowadays .
How beautiful ...
How gorgeous , my angels .
If only they were artificial they 'd bloom even in the snow .
Mr. Dvorak 's so nervous he smokes all the time .
Come on , Mili ! Don 't keep wandering off .
They exercise so nicely .
My pretties , I know something far better .
- What is it ? - Not afraid , are you ?
Laget , the mass-murderer .
He murdered every day ... and every night .
- They look so alive ... - Stop acting so stupid .
This is a wax museum , right ?
Now , in dread of His wrath let 's all see the bath .
Lights !
- Will there be water and steam ? - Shut up .
It 's just wax museum .
This is the St. Francis Spa ,
where people come to fix a flaw .
This lady will give the baths a try ...
She smiles sweetly at this young guy .
Then sits to calmly in the tub ,
but he 's planning more than a scrub .
Old baths .
How much nicer our bathroom is .
- She looks like the milk woman . - Ssh ! You 're not at the dairy .
Darkness .
This bloke had the plague so he hanged himself dead .
He was decisive and brave and didn 't want it to spread .
He hangs here by the neck , and no one can bring him back .
- He looks alive . - He 's dead , hanged .
This unfortunate lad was killed by murderer Moore .
It only took a second with this iron bar .
Sweet , blue-eyed Moore had everyone baffled .
He murdered 6 people and ended at the scaffold .
There he is .
- I knew it . - The hell you did . You 're nuts .
I can 't even take you to a wax museum . She 's an idiot ...
This way please ,
toward our wax gnome by the name of Tom .
He 's alive !
The show is through for most of you .
But men whose nerves are strong might like to come along .
Here we have various diseases ... pox and syphilis ...
Both contagious .
How horrible to die this way .
Indeed .
But modern doctors
can protect us .
Like ...
our kind Dr. Bettelheim .
You still feel these tests are necessary , Mr. Kopfrkingl ?
Doctor , I have intercourse only with my beloved wife .
I 'm afraid to seem like a bit of a hypochondriac ,
but I worry about being infected at the crematorium .
You don 't deal with corpses . Infection is impossible .
How glad I am that you are our neighbour ,
and that my son is friends with your nephew .
Mili wanders around and today that 's dangerous .
I hear martial law has been declared in the border region .
That will mean hell for many people .
Violence never pays , Mr. Kopfrkingl .
It 's not a reliable principle of power .
This is 20th-century Europe in a civilized world .
Aggressors are always defeated in the end .
If you think it necessary , Mr. Kopfrkingl , come again .
Mr. Kopfrkingl ... Come have a look .
Banana flies , used for heredity tests .
This one is a ' Drosophila Funebris ' , the funeral fly .
Would you like the collection ?
I 'll let it go cheap ... for just a pinch of morphine .
I have a weakness for such ... decorations .
We have a butterfly pinned on the bathroom wall .
But where would I get morphine ? I don 't even smoke .
That friend of yours is a chemical engineer ...
Mr. Reinke is out of town . It 's mobilisation , Mr. Fenek .
When he comes back then . I still have a bit left .
I came in early
so I could see you .
There are better things to look at .
How long have you been living like this ?
Do you find meaning in life by cleaning every morning ?
Times are hard - it 's mobilisation .
You need someone to cling to , to protect you .
Let 's talk about it later tonight .
What 's the matter ?
I frightened Mrs. Liskova .
Mr. Kopfrkingl , a crematorium is no place for jokes .
You 're right , bad timing .
I wanted to invite her to our place for a change of pace .
Maybe some other time .
Well , Mr. Kopfrkingl ! Do come in .
MASSAGE PARLOUR
How sweet and thoughtful of you .
- I bought this for Zina . - The young lady has a client .
Perhaps you 'd consider another ? They all say how nice you are .
You 'd have to wait a bit for Miss Dagmar .
Pity you only come once a month .
You should honour us more often .
Maybe I should .
I can afford to now .
I have an agent ,
and it 's healthy .
Ah , Miss Dagmar . You didn 't have to wait long after all .
- Farewell , goodbye . - Goodbye . Here ...
Mr. Kopfrkingl , I 've waited all month . Let me just tidy up .
I wouldn 't like my Zina 's present to be crumpled .
We have a new man at the ovens , Mr. Dvorak .
He helps prepare the coffins .
He smoked from nerves when he started .
He 's not so nervous now .
Thank God he no longer smokes so much .
Mr. Strauss is a success at selling cremations .
People at sweet shops are gentle ,
kind ,
and pleasant .
Alright , let 's go ...
I need another agent , a seller of toys ...
or cosmetics . Either would serve .
I must take care of my family .
We have a beautiful and blessed home .
I must take care of you even better .
I 'd like to take on another agent .
Mr. Dvorak no longer smokes so much .
But haven 't I already mentioned that ?
You look so sad lately , Lakme .
anything worrying you ?
Any problems ?
Our angel 's birthday is coming up .
I bought her an outfit .
Let 's hope her Kaja 's as much a family man as I am
Even these died on us . Everything dies here .
Mrs. Liskova is quitting . She couldn 't get used to it here .
Such a shame , Mrs. Liskova . Why so suddenly ?
Now I won 't be able to take you out .
We 're so busy too , and German soldiers stand at the border .
Even Mr. Vrana can 't light it .
You 're so upset , but why would they occupy us ?
Violence never pays .
This is 20th-century Europe in a civilized world .
When does Miss Carska 's turn come , Mr. Dvorak ?
Seventh .
The first this afternoon . No waiting for her , poor ...
Miss Carska .
She was just about to get married .
I 'll make sure she 's perfectly ready .
Mr. Kopfrkingl , I don 't want to trouble you ,
but have you got the morphine ?
I told you Mr. Reinke is out of town . Be patient .
You can 't worry about morphine with the Germans at the border .
They 've convened a conference . It may mean war , and Miss Carska
was just about to get married .
" How horrible it is to lose
" so many loved ones in their prime .
" Frost burns flowers ' flushed cheeks ,
" and the Angel of Death takes his toll . "
An educated speaker .
They 're playing Dvorak 's ' Largo ' , Mr. Dvorak .
In 75 minutes Miss Carska 's ashes will fill an urn .
But not her soul .
That can 't be .
It will be reincarnated , liberated , as the Tibetans say .
It will rise into the ether .
You know , premature death is a blessing only if it relieves
... great suffering .
I 'd like to leave , too .
I think I 'd be happier in a boiler room .
What 's wrong now , Mr. Dvorak ?
I thought you had overcome your fears .
I was even telling my dear wife you smoked less .
Boiler work is a humiliation .
Help yourselves , dear children , Kaja , girls , Vojta ...
Much has happened since the border regions were occupied .
Lovely music ...
Let 's see what they say in the papers .
CHERRY BOMBS , SKY ROCKETS
Mili , what odd ideas you have . Never swallow a cherry bomb .
Understand You could be crippled for life .
Will you take a photo , Kaja ?
A photograph eternally preserves the present moment .
We take photos at work too , but without the finger-waggling .
They buy them as souvenirs - the survivors , that is .
Did anyone ever wake up in their coffin ?
Oh really , Kaja ... it hasn 't happened yet .
Not even Miss Carska ,
although so young and about to be married .
People do wake up in coffins . I read about it .
Only if the person wasn 't dead .
But it would be impossible after 75 minutes in the furnace .
In some human countries they even burn animals .
You 'll be cremated too , Enchantress .
One day you won 't even recognise your present self .
Cremation is humane .
And rids people of the fear of death .
My dear children ... do not fear cremation .
Zina , why don 't you play for our guests ?
How about Mahler 's ' Songs on the Death of Children ' ?
Or something more lively ... Danse Macabre by Saint-Saens ?
I 'm taking Mili to a boxing match .
My enchantress almost forgot to tell me about it .
You 've never seen a boxing match , neither have I.
It seems a brutal sport .
But I 'm looking forward to it .
One ... two ...
You 're seeing a truly manly sport for once .
- I think it rather brutal . - Tough , yes , but that 's good .
You must be brave . Boxing is for fighters . Man against man .
Why must I do this ... Can we never be on time ?
Excuse me . These are our seats . Beat it !
That pale-skinned girl over there
reminds me of a waitress at our club .
- Look ! - Shut up .
- What if he breaks his leg ? - What ? Drop it !
My angel nearly forgot about your invitation today .
- Is he bleeding ? - There shouldn 't be any blood .
- Clean your glasses , Mili . - They 'll knock their teeth out !
- Are they dancing ? - They 're in the ring , damn it .
They 'll hurt him .
The referee doesn 't box . Watch the two men in shorts .
White shorts is a Union man and red is a butcher 's apprentice .
- A butcher ! There 'll be blood ! - This isn 't a slaughterhouse .
Now shut up , stupid , and watch .
- You said he wouldn 't get hurt . - It was a mistake . Now shut up .
It is slaughterhouse ! There 's blood everywhere . Why did we come ?
Get out of here , you nut ! She 's headed for the asylum
three , four , five , six
seven , eight , nine ...
Is the apprentice dead , Daddy ?
Death is the only certainty .
COME JOIN US !
Ah , Christmas ... a truly blessed time .
You look radiant , my angel .
Why don 't I hang you up among these pretty angels
and all this beauty ?
Don 't make them suffer . They 're suffocating .
Ana is coming soon to kill them .
Why is Ana coming ? Can 't you do it ?
Dear child , of course I could , but I don 't like to .
Ana is used to it . She 's a good old soul .
Come , children , we needn 't watch .
Leave her here . My sweet one enjoys the entrails .
One of them is dead by now ... if Ana hit it well .
It 's soul is already in the ether .
Now the second one is dead .
You may play with their soul-bladders .
But those are really their lungs .
Their true souls may have just reincarnated ...
into cats , maybe .
We may have once eaten Enchantress as a carp .
We may even eat her again sometime as ...
something else .
But before enjoying our repast we 'll wait for Mr. Reinke .
A pretty Christmas tree . Any carp ?
Two . My angel is frying them on our little home furnace .
Her blessed mother used to make jellied carp ,
a foreign recipe , but we do it Czech style .
With carp , okay . But don 't you feel our blood ?
We 're fighting for the cause and you fry carp the Czech way ?
I thought you opposed violence , wanted justice and salvation .
This republic is a bastion for our enemies .
It 's a humanitarian state with good laws .
For instance , the one on cremation .
We will implement a higher moral code , a new world order .
You are an honest sensitive , dutiful man .
You are strong and brave . A pure Germanic soul .
Listen , Karel , we want to put you to the test .
On March 6th there will be some kind of celebration
at the Jewish Town Hall here in Prague .
Get your old Jew Bettelheim to invite you ,
the one who got rich curing VD .
Listen to their talk , their opinions ...
It 's a way of helping the poor unfortunate Jews .
How is it going to help them ?
They are poor , misguided people who understand nothing .
They fight against our Fuehrer because they don 't get it .
They are a lost nation which understands nothing .
You can help them by finding out what they say and think ...
Walter won 't be having almonds today , dear .
I bought you an application to join the Party .
Become a member . There 's still time .
I have to go now .
The wife and I are spending Christmas Eve at the casino .
We usually don 't bring our wives .
We already have excellent companions there .
Gorgeous blondes only .
Have a look . Of course , only Party members are allowed .
Germans like you and me .
" Mother tongue "
" I declare ... No Jewish blood ... I claim German citizenship ... "
All blondes ... I 'll have to get used to it .
Now it 's really Christmas . Candles at home , for once .
I usually see them on the catafalque and on graves .
I wonder what the Bettelheims are doing .
Celebrating Christmas like us even though they 're Jews ?
He 's rich , the poor man , living off other 's misfortunes .
It 's Christmas Eve , my dears , and the temple of death is idle .
No cremating today , but they should cremate on Christmas
when so many souls need emancipating ,
need liberating into space to find new bodies .
Christmas should be for the dead , too .
At least the carp have profited .
Just as a token . I don 't drink . I 'm an abstainer .
Germans don 't drink either .
That humane nation also has a cremation law .
A great future awaits them . Unfortunately ...
I hope we , too , belong to this chosen people
who will implement a higher moral code .
Blood is blood and cannot be renounced .
Do you still feel it 's necessary , Mr. Kopfrkingl ?
What kind of blood do I have , Doctor ?
It 'll be negative , as usual .
That 's not what I meant . I was wondering ...
whether it 's Czech blood ...
or German ?
It 's impossible to tell .
Well , then , whether it 's Slavic or Germanic ?
There 's no difference in blood . The same as with human ashes .
You yourself always say that - whether French or Spanish ,
doctor or clerk ... It 's all the same .
Isn 't the Jewish community
planning some kind of celebration with pretty songs ?
You mean Chevra Suda , a dinner at the Funeral Brotherhood Hall .
It won 't be so nice this year . Would you like to come ?
At the Funeral Brotherhood Hall .
What a magnificent tremolo .
They called the Fuehrer a fraud and a blackguard .
What a gorgeous voice ...
So sad ...
Didn 't they say that Party members would be eliminated ?
Yes , there were lots of them there , speaking , eating ...
And that cantor , those high notes ...
So they said they 'd destroy Germany and assume power ?
Yes , assume power ... And the singing was so soft ,
so heartrending ...
They said they 'd bury Germany ?
The Reich !
Yes , yes . It was like a grand funeral .
You 're right ... It 's heavenly here ,
and no one is suffering .
Soon there will be no suffering anywhere : Warsaw , Paris ,
London , New York ...
They 'll be liberated just like Bohemia and Moravia .
Not even horses need suffer . The Reich 's army is mechanised .
You didn 't see any horses when Prague was occupied , right ?
It 's all mechanised , automated - just like your crematorium .
The Fuehrer is building a paradise .
- Good evening . - We must celebrate our victory !
Hold on , hold on ...
- Cheers ! - Quick !
I 'm an abstainer . I don 't even smoke .
Today doesn 't count .
I 'll remember March 15th my whole ... life .
Just a token drop , then .
We have enemies , Karl .
Even at the crematorium .
We rely on you .
You 're our only man there , and you 're a Party member .
What 's the situation ?
Some people just don 't understand ,
like Zajic ,
Fenek ,
Beran ,
Podzimkova ,
Pelikan ,
or the porter ... Vrana .
There 's something wrong with his liver , but still ...
He 's an inveterate enemy of the Reich .
Or ... Liskova .
She used to clean but quit last year . We can find her easily .
And the director of my temple of death ...
He also lacks the proper attitude towards the Reich
I 'd like to burn all Germans in these ovens , he said once .
I don 't think he should remain director .
We 'll take care of it .
And what about those poor , unfortunate Jews of yours ?
You employ two of them .
Well , Mr. Strauss ...
is a good ...
decent man ...
who likes music , a good worker .
He may be doing it only for the money .
He confided to me that he disagrees with the Germans .
Dr. Bettelheim 's a good man too ,
but doesn 't understand either .
I 'm afraid he 's influenced his nephew , Jan.
I don 't like him . He makes Mili wander .
His housekeeper , Ana ...
She isn 't Jewish .
She killed our Christmas carp ...
But she 's probably also under his influence .
Jews can 't be re-educated . A misguided , unfortunate nation .
As you say , it 's the same with music ...
look , the Spartans killed sickly children .
Some think it cruel ,
but , indeed , how merciful , especially for those children .
They 'd have been unhappy ,
and how much better for the nation .
Listen , Karl , your wife 's mother used to make jellied carp .
You called it a foreign recipe .
But that 's the Jewish way .
Lakme 's mother was a Jew .
Your dark-haired Lakme told me
that you only spoke Czech until I spoke of your German blood .
She ' forgot about ' my invitation to the boxing-match .
She didn 't like your joining the Party .
What 'll she say when you send the kids to a German school ?
You see what she 's done to Mili . The boy is soft , effeminate .
That 's the covert way they operate .
They start with the family , with the children .
How long , Mr. Kopfrkingl , have you been married ?
Our blessed marriage has lasted for 19 years .
We met by the leopards at the zoo .
At the predator pavilion .
We must make sacrifices , Mr. Kopfrkingl .
I 'm afraid you 'll never hold a higher post .
There 's no difference in blood . Dr. Bettelheim says so .
It makes all the difference . Purity of blood is essential .
Under the just , new order inferior blood must go .
Isn 't your Dr. Bettelheim a Jew ?
Lakme should realise she isn 't worthy of you .
It 's incompatible with the honour of an honest and healthy man .
Karl , many problems await her .
Director , I couldn 't get here on time .
I had several unexpected meetings .
That isn 't like you , Mr. Kopfrkingl .
But in these crazy times everything is changing .
Yes , we must expect certain changes .
You 've nearly stopped smoking , Mr. Dvorak .
Mr. Pelikan will take this fair lady for viewing .
Okay , Mr. Pelikan , she seems just about ready .
What about my morphine ?
You 'll get none from me , Mr. Fenek .
You won 't be on my conscience . I am an honest , healthy man .
If you don 't stop pestering me I 'll report you .
Addiction is a vice incompatible with honour .
One more word and I 'll have you put in an asylum .
Perhaps , Mr. Vrana , you didn 't notice that the fires went out !
And so they arrested Beran , Zajic and the director .
It couldn 't be helped .
Mr. Fenek asked for morphine again .
He 's a weak , destroyed man .
Mr. Prachar drinks , and his poor son , Vojta ...
Who else is there ... ?
It 's just that butcher 's apprentice ... That boxer .
Where did you get this , Mili ?
I 've been to that youth club , where they train .
Their flyer said , " Come join us . "
How great to have a boxer for a friend .
You need to be tough and brave .
You 've got my German blood in your veins .
You 'll be going to a German school next year .
A boxer is better than that Jan Bettelheim .
And what does the boxer say ? What do you talk about ?
He says he has to train hard to be able to knock ...
the Germans ' teeth out .
That 's all wrong , Mili .
When you and Zina come back from your aunt 's
I 'll explain to you how things are .
Go and be good .
Why don 't you dress up ...
since we 're alone ?
We 'll have a special dinner .
You can put on your black party dress .
You 've only worn it a few times .
Then we 'll take a bath in our lovely bathroom
as would befit a Roman feast .
You see , I 'm to be promoted to director .
And isn 't it our wedding anniversary ?
Or that of our blessed encounter by the leopards at the zoo ?
No ? We 'll pretend it is .
Didn 't you enjoy the meal ?
One should savour every day of one 's life ...
as if it were the last .
Silent one , the world is open to us ,
as are the heavens across which no cloud has passed for 19 years .
But I noticed that the bathroom fan is broken .
I 've attached a rope so that we can get to it from a chair .
Do you hear this lovely song ?
How poor is he who dies ...
without knowing the beauty of music .
You at least loved music .
Come , my silent one , let 's draw a bath .
It won 't be too hot for you .
Open the fan , dearest .
What if I hanged you , my dearest ?
May I speak to Director Kopfrkingl ?
Please take a seat .
I was just reading ...
May I offer you a cognac ? Or some Czech plum brandy ?
No thank you , I 'm an abstainer . I don 't even smoke .
The Dalai-Lama has died .
Our blessed land of Tibet has been seeking
the reincarnation of Buddha , our Saviour .
After years of searching we have found him at last .
The throne in Lhasa awaits you , Rimpoche .
I shall come for you .
We shall then leave for the Himalayas ,
our blessed homeland paradise .
A painful duty has befallen me .
As new director of this grand temple of death ,
my first cremation will be that of my own beloved wife .
19 years of happiness have ended in her tragic death .
But truly death can be a blessing .
A great blessing if it spares us from suffering .
It can free us from the terror and anxiety which might ...
have awaited us .
That 's the last straw ...
You have returned to where you come from .
Your soul has been liberated and now soars in the ether .
Even the old Teutons , dear friends , burned their dead ,
entrusted them to the flames .
I bid you farewell , my angel ,
as crematorium director and as your loving husband .
But we must make sacrifices .
The only certainty in life
is death
and the implementation of a propitious new order .
The Fuehrer 's new , fortunate Europe and death
are the only certainties that we humans have .
Heil !
The flames , my sweet , will not hurt you .
I 've also retired Mr. Vrana , the porter .
He was too old .
As well as Mrs. Podzimkova , the cleaning woman .
She once said the incinerators scared her ,
so I relieved her of her fears .
I 'll keep the others for the time being .
But Mili worries me .
He is more and more effeminate . He never did take after me .
- And he wanders about so much . - Hedvika , throw me the soap !
His mother was half Jewish ... and it shows .
- Good evening . - Good evening .
We won 't intrude . Good evening .
Mili is a Mischling of the second degree ,
a quarter Jew according to Reich law .
I 'm afraid they won 't let him go to high school ,
and you can forget the Hitler Youth .
And he wanders about so much . I think he likes soldiers .
We 're almost at war ...
He 's romantic enough to join up .
Children are always a trial .
It 's Saturday and nothing 's burning at my temple of death .
At least you 'll be able to have a look at everything .
At the place your father started 20 years ago .
- Where 're you going , Mili ? - Just out .
To walk a bit on a fine day so he won 't just wander about .
These are revolutionary times .
We must bravely bear ... our pain and suffering .
Your blessed mother ...
I wonder what she 's been reincarnated into ?
Would you like a cream coffin or a vanilla wreath ?
Both , I guess .
Just the wreath or you won 't eat your dinner .
Let 's walk through the cemetery .
I used to take walks here before I became director .
Go on , go on ! Don 't say a word .
You think you 're at a carnival ?
You see how crazy she is ? She thinks she 's at the fair .
Stop or I 'll kill you !
Come along ... It 's nothing .
Did you enjoy your vanilla wreath ?
That 's good .
One shouldn 't desecrate a sacred place .
That 's not for you , Mili .
Look , isn 't that a nice gravestone ?
Do you see there ? Greek torches ...
like in ancient Sparta .
They 've been burning ever since we hired new people .
But they 're not burning .
Come along .
This is where people are turned into dust .
Don 't be frightened , Mili . I 'm here with you .
Mr. Dvorak ...
this is the preparation room .
This one is nailed shut because it won 't go for viewing .
The ceremony is Monday and then straight into the oven .
It holds a brave pure-blooded German .
No weak , effeminate soul . Pure origins .
Wipe your glasses so you won 't ruin your eyes .
Mr. Dvorak wanted to get rid of this bar ,
but I said it might come in handy sometime .
There 's no difference between human ashes .
Mili , what about if I
put you in with him ?
Daddy ...
Rimpoche , it 's time .
The throne awaits you .
Our beloved Tibet awaits its ruler .
The wall obscuring your vision has fallen .
The heavens have opened , stars shine above ...
You will save the world .
You are Buddha .
Yes , the heavens have opened , the stars above are infinite ...
As I read for years in my book about Tibet by David-Neel :
" free all creatures from the suffering that awaits them . "
I must save one more good soul .
Save her from the suffering in store for her
in the coming blissful life which awaits .
Wait until next Saturday , my son .
So that 's it , Mr. Kopfrkingl ...
We have to test certain ... as you know ...
But it 's all top secret .
You have 20 years experience ...
A gas furnace of the future ...
You 'll be the expert in charge . But absolute secrecy is vital .
It 's top secret .
Naturally , I understand completely .
Equipment for incinerating as many people as possible
to free them from the shackles of this world ,
and let them dissolve into the ether .
What a tremendous opportunity .
My crematorium takes 75 minutes to change each corpse into dust .
If we had huge furnaces to hold a hundred ,
five hundred , a thousand ,
it could be done in 10 minutes .
Entire halls in constant operation would be economical .
Hundreds fed into one side , ashes streaming out the other .
They 'd get mixed , true , but ashes don 't differ ...
And liberated souls would gush from the chimneys .
We could quickly liberate all humanity , the whole world .
Poor Mr. Prachar , Vojta ... What luck for the Bettelheims ,
for all those Jews at the celebration ...
If I gave them hope that they wouldn 't suffer ...
If I could tell them about reincarnation ...
Mr. Kopfrkingl !
Mr. Kopfrkingl ! You must be overworked .
You know , a person wouldn 't have to be completely dead .
In such huge halls constantly in operation
once you entered you 'd never come out alive .
But absolute secrecy is essential .
Yes , secret ...
Absolute secrecy is essential .
I 've been put in charge of a huge project .
I 'm leaving my temple of death , but you can still have a look .
Truly , Zina , there is still no news of Mili .
He must have wandered off quite far .
Where are you going , Zina ?
Please come another time , Kaja . I 've something to show Zina .
Should I come next week ?
Yes , my angel will be so glad . Do you have your camera ?
- No . - You don 't ...
A pity , you could have taken an everlasting keepsake .
No one will suffer any longer . I am working on a great project .
Let 's go through the cemetery .
I used to take walks here ... It may be my last time .
Excuse me , have you seen my wife ? She ran off a week ago .
You met us here , remember ? Have you seen her ?
You were here with some boy . I 've already waited a week .
Maybe she 'll come back by herself , the idiot .
Look around where your father worked for twenty years .
That 's a bit disrespectful . Don 't even look , angel .
Look , sunshine , at this lovely gravestone .
This is where people are turned into dust .
But the ovens are small . I 'm planning something much larger
... and faster .
This is the preparation room .
The coffin 's nailed because it goes right to the oven Monday .
No , that wouldn 't be proper .
This piano teacher will be far more suitable .
See that bar ? I told Mr. Dvorak it would come in handy .
We must go .
The wall around us has fallen .
Stars and eternal light are before us .
Now you will save the world .
Rimpoche , the nation and humanity are waiting .
I 'm glad you came . I will soon come among you .
I shall mount my throne .
But my poor unfortunate daughter is a quarter Jewish .
I haven 't yet saved her .
Don 't worry we 'll take care of her .
We 'll take care of her ourselves .
You 've work to do , Mr.Kopfrkingl . Lots of work .
For the nation . For all mankind .
No one will suffer . I 'll save them all .
I 'll save them all .
The whole world .
The End